<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A further vindication of the Church of England, with advice to all emperours and kings of the Romish faith Also some arguments used to prove the Church of Rome no true church, but antichristian and bloody. By William Chandler.</title>
            <author>Chandler, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1935A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229536</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899231</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899231</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152622</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78568)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152622)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2309:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A further vindication of the Church of England, with advice to all emperours and kings of the Romish faith Also some arguments used to prove the Church of Rome no true church, but antichristian and bloody. By William Chandler.</title>
                  <author>Chandler, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152622:1"/>
            <p>A FURTHER VINDICATION OF THE <hi>Church of England,</hi> WITH Advice to all Emperours and Kings of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith.</p>
            <p>Alſo ſome Arguments uſed to prove the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> no true Church, but Antichriſtian and Bloody.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Chandler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author, 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152622:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152622:2"/>
            <head>To the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, <hi>CHALES</hi> the Second, by the Grace of God, King of Great <hi>Brittain, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt gracious and dread Soveraign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving made a moſt diligent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the ſtate of the Church of God, militant upon Earth, I do find that it is not limited to any one Country or Nation, as the <hi>Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> held; who fondly imagined the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church of God to be confined to a Corner of <hi>Africa,</hi> in which they dwelt; nor yet incloſed within one Biſhops Dioceſs, or Juriſdiction, as the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, who uncharitably exclude all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Heaven, putting them into the State of Damnation, who are not ſubject to their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152622:3"/>Biſhop; vainly pretending to be truly Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick or Univerſal; as we do believe in our holy Creed. The Apoſtles preached not to one Country or Nation only, but to the whole World, according to our Lords Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; <hi>Go teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak ſomething of this perſecuted Epiſcopal Church of <hi>England,</hi> whom the Lord, by his Providence, hath made Your Majeſty Overſeer: This Church, which was firſt planted by <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> ſome years before <hi>Rome,</hi> according to the pureſt way, as he had it from Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, the great Biſhop of our Souls; and ſo hath continued a true Church, through much Perſecution by the Heathen, and by the common Enemy the Papiſts, and by the Diſſenters. As <hi>Gamaliel</hi> told the <hi>Jews;</hi> take heed, if it be of God ye cannot over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it, leſt you be fighters againſt God: No doubt this Church of <hi>England</hi> is of God, and cannot be overthrown. You have heard of the Perſecution in Queen <hi>Maries</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152622:3"/>days, how ſhe burnt twelve Biſhops and Doctors, who ſealed it with their Blood in the Fire, and <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, who ſealed it with his Royal Blood alſo; the Blood of the Martyrs is the Seed and Seal of a true Church.</p>
            <p>We moſt humbly thank Your Majeſty, that Your Majeſty hath taken ſuch care for this perſecuted Church, which without doubt God prizes as the Apple of his Eye, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving it from all theſe Eminent dangers.</p>
            <p>And we moſt humbly thank Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that Your moſt Royal Majeſty hath been pleaſed to put thoſe good Laws in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, againſt thoſe Enemies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that many of them have received Juſtice according to the merit of their Cauſe. The Lord bleſs Your Majeſty, for taking ſuch ſpecial care over both Church and State, for the good of us your unworthy Subjects, not doubting but Your Majeſty will have the ſame care, ſo long as Breath ſhall remain in Your Royal Majeſty, which the Lord of his Mercy grant for many Years to come, that we may receive the Benefit, and give
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152622:4"/>God the Glory: And all this we beg for the ſake of our Bleſſed Redeemer Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>A word to his Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> under Grace and Favour. O Royal <hi>James!</hi> live for ever; Son to one of the beſt Kings that ever reigned; though <hi>David</hi> were a Man after Gods own Heart, and <hi>Solomon</hi> was a wiſe Man, yet Your Royal Father had leſs Errors than any of them. O Royal <hi>James,</hi> Heir to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> after Your Royal Brothers Deceaſe; as the caſe now ſtands, the Lord bleſs Your Lives with all bleſſings Spiritual and Temporal; and if ever Providence ordereth it ſo that You be Crowned King of <hi>England,</hi> and of the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions thereunto belonging, that you may come to it in peace, and not ſwim to it in Blood, for then it will prove to you a Curſe, and not a Bleſſing.</p>
            <p>The Lord grant that you may maintain the true Government both in Church and State, as it now ſtandeth, as Your Royal Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth at this time, and your Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152622:4"/>of ever bleſſed memory hath done, and as your Royal Grandfather King <hi>James</hi> hath done; eſpecially this Epiſcopal Church of <hi>England,</hi> which Your Royal Grandfather told Your Royal Father, he having ſtudied to find the true Church of God, he was very well ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Church of <hi>England</hi> was the neareſt to the Primitive Church planted by the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>I ſhall add ſomething more concerning the common Enemy the Papiſts, and Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour Chriſt ſaith, The time ſhall come, when they that kill you ſhall think they do God good Service: So did the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters when they killed one of the beſt Kings that ever reigned; and ſo would the Papiſts, if they could have killed our King that now is; you ſee how they tollerated Murder, Treaſon, Perjury, and Rebellion; and he that could have killed Gods Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, ſhould have done God good Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; yea, it was thought he ſhould have been Sainted for his good Service: Yea, this temporal Man of Sin might as well have Sainted the Spiritual Man of Sin, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152622:5"/>as to have Sainted theſe Prieſts and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, whom Satan had put into their Hearts to do his will; let this temporal Man of ſin pretend what he will, yet this wicked Plot, to kill our Soveraign Lord the King, came from the Devil, who is the original of all ſin; for they reckoned to have ſacrificed His, Royal Body to God, for the Honour of their Church; when God tells them to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey is better than Sacrifice; that is, thou ſhalt do no Murder, and Rebellion is as the ſin of Witchcraft.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour Chriſt ſaith, I have choſen twelve, and one of them was a Devil: but what ſhall we call theſe Prieſts and Jeſuits ſent by the Man of ſin, to kill Gods Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, the King? We may call them, as the Devil ſaid their Name is, <hi>Legion,</hi> for they are many. <hi>Judas</hi> betrayed his Lord and Maſter for thirty pieces of Silver, but theſe Bloody Prieſts were to murder their Lord and Maſter for a bigger ſum. <hi>Judas,</hi> when he had betrayed Chriſt, repented, and ſaid, <hi>I have ſinned, in that I have betrayed innocent Blood;</hi> but theſe Men were ſo far from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152622:5"/>that they would not confeſs upon their Tryal, though it were proved by two of the Kings Witneſſes.</p>
            <p>You ſee then, <hi>Judas,</hi> for all he was count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Devil, yet ſhewed more of a Chriſtian in repenting, and in laying down his Money again, than thoſe Jeſuitical Devils, which would not confeſs the Fact of their Deviliſh Deſigns, though it was proved againſt them. The Wiſe Man ſaith; <hi>He that covereth his Sin ſhall not proſper, but he that confeſſeth and forſaketh his Sin ſhall find Mercy:</hi> Yea, when the Man of Sin heard of the good ſucceſs of this wicked Plot going on ſo well, the Conclave of Hell ſang <hi>te Deum,</hi> and the Man of Sin gave them his Bleſſing; you ſee for all they ſung to God for Joy, and the Man of Sin gave them his Bleſſing; their myrth was turned into ſadneſs, and their bleſſing into a Curſe upon them, as <hi>TYB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN</hi> will witneſs, and many Spectators that beheld them. O my Beloved, take ſpecial notice, that this Plot was not from God, but of themſelves, with the help of Satan, and came
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152622:6"/>to nothing, as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> ſaith: I beſeech you all good People that fear God, to take ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial notice of the Death of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey,</hi> which diſcovers more of inhumanity in their Religion, than any other of their wicked devices; if all the Devils in Hell had been let looſe to their aſſiſtance, they could not have done more than theſe wicked Men did; they enticed him with flattering and lying words; as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; they told him if he would go along with them, they would ſhew him more of that wicked Conclave; and he being a Juſtice of the Peace, he might apprehend them: this honeſt Juſtice being willing to ſerve the King, according to his Oath, went with them, and they had him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a place, where they ſecured him from the help of all his Friends; there, as I may ſay, they opened Hell Gates, and let out the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, who fell upon him, and wickedly mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him, he being without any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but the mercy of Chriſt Jeſus upon his Soul.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152622:6"/>
            <p>O all you Emperours, Kings, Princes, and Dukes, whom God hath ordained as his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents to execute his will upon Earth, take care you come not near the man of Sin, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to his deceivable bloody Doctrine, who allows his Prieſts to colour their Coats with the blood of Kings and Princes, and to waſh their Altars with the blood of Gods Saints, and garniſh their Sepulchres with the blood of Gods Elect; as our Saviour ſaith; and will not God avenge the blood of his Elect, that cry to him day and night? yea, he will avenge them ſpeedily.</p>
            <p>You ſee this Scripture fulfilled quickly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey,</hi> how God did avenge his Blood upon his Murderers, witneſs <hi>TYB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN,</hi> and many that beheld them.</p>
            <p>All the Maſſacres, both in <hi>France,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, the Chronicles ſpeak of, in mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering many hundred of poor innocent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, was done by that bloody Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152622:7"/>
            <p>All you Emperours, Kings, and Dukes, whom God hath ordered to execute his Will upon Earth, have a care that you do not oblige your ſelves to the Man of ſin, by ſwearing Allegiance, or Canonical obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for then he makes you under the Man of Sin and Satan, his Vaſſals and Slaves, that when he calls his Councils, you muſt agree to his unlawful Decrees, which if you do not, he will put you into the ſtate of Damnation, as he thinketh.</p>
            <p>We ſee how this Church of <hi>England</hi> hath been approved on, going through the Firy-Tryal, witneſs the twelve Doctors and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days, who ſealed it by Blood and Fire; and <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bleſſed memory, ſealed it with his Royal Blood alſo, who without doubt is now a Saint in Heaven; which except we could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a better place of happineſs than ever was ſpoken of in Scripture, we could never deſire to go to a better place of Joy, than where this good King is gone, by the mercy of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152622:7"/>Jeſus Chriſt, who dyed for the Priviledge of this Church and State, hoping, and not doubting but his Royal Iſſue will maintain the ſame, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Royal Fathers laſt Will and Teſtament, that they ſhould take care of the Church, and love one another, then will their poor Subjects love their Royal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty above meaſure, in taking ſuch care of this true Church of God, wherein contains all our happineſs, both of Soul and Body; then will God love us, when we love him and his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent; for God is Love, and in him is no ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred; then will he dwell in us, and we in him, then will God bleſs us with bleſſings both tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and ſpiritual, wherein our whole happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, both of Soul and Body, conſiſts.</p>
            <p>The honour of a King is to have the love of his Subjects; and what is the comfort of the Subjects, but a Godly and a pious King; which the Lord grant to us ſuch a meaſure of grace, that we may, every one of us, love one another, but eſpecially our King, and then ſhall <hi>Babylon</hi> mourn, but <hi>Zion</hi> ſhall rejoyce.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152622:8"/>
            <p>One thing more I ſhall not forget to put His Majeſties Subjects in mind of, That if ever His Majeſty ſhould call a Parliament, that they chuſe no Diſſenters; for if God do not bleſs them to agree in matters of Religion, he will not bleſs them when they come to ſit upon mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of State.</p>
            <p>In the Fifth of the <hi>Galatians,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>The Works of the Fleſh are theſe, Adultery, Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Laſciviouſneſs, Witchcraft, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Variance, Emulation, Wrath, Strife, Hereſie, Sedition, Envying, Murder, Drunkenneſs,</hi> which do appear to be ſome of the ſins of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and that they that do ſuch things ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of Heaven: <hi>But the Fruits of the Spirit is, joy, love, peace, long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, gentleneſs, goodneſs, Faith, meekneſs, temperance,</hi> againſt ſuch there is no Law; of which you can find very little in the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Man of ſin, but quite contrary to the ſaid good Fruits.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152622:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A word in anſwer to the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> whom a Perſon of our Neighbourhood told me, that they did atteſt they had no hand in the Death of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt: Which I wiſh from my Heart that it were true, which I fear is not, becauſe the <hi>Scots</hi> ſold him for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain hundreds of thouſand pounds; becauſe that bleſſed King ſpake in his little Book, called his <hi>Meditation,</hi> that he was ſorry he was ſold for more than his Saviour. Without doubt they ſold him to the other Diſſenters, which at laſt Crucified him. If it were a ſin in <hi>Judas</hi> for ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and betraying of his Lord and Maſter, I fear it was a ſin in them for betraying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of their Lord and Maſter the King. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> had ſome remorſe in him, and ſeemed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in, throwing down the Money, and ſaying, <hi>I have ſinned, in that I have betrayed the innocent Blood;</hi> and ſo I hope will theſe repent from the bottom of their Hearts, that their Souls may be ſaved in the day of the Lord; the which I beſeech the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to grant unto them through his Grace and Mercy, and that they may return to us again from whence they went out; and that they may renounce that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152622:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>wicked Covenant, if they have taken it; that they together with us, and we with them, may ſerve God together in love, that this Church militant may fit us for the Church triumphant, where we may all meet together to ſing <hi>Halilu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> to the great God that reigns for ever; where there is no diviſion nor diſſention, but all love and unity, which the Lord of his Mercy grant.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:152622:9"/>
            <head>THE EXCELLENCY OF THE GRACE OF CHARITY Set forth in a DISCOURSE ON 1 Corinth. XIII. 13.</head>
            <p>By <hi>William Chandler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author, 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:152622:10"/>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152622:10"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. XIII. 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Now abideth faith, hope, and charity, theſe three, but the greateſt of theſe is charity.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>FAith is the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeen: Faith is the groundwork of our Salvation; by Faith we believe that Chriſt came into the World, laid down his life freely for us Sinners, was born of a pure Virgin, preached the Goſpel of our Salvation, that he was crucified, dead, and buried, that he roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the third day, and aſcended into Heaven, and there ſitteth at the right hand of God making Interceſſion for us Sinners. By Hope is to be underſtood that Hope which is annext to Faith, that we obtain the Fruits of our Faith, the ſalvation of all our Souls. Again, having a ſound Faith, made up with Good Works, we hope we ſhall obtain the ſalvation of all our Souls, which Chriſt hath merited by his death and paſſion; and by his Free Grace and Mercy we hope to obtain the Kingdom of Heaven, which by hope and patience we have long wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for. Charity is ſo great a Grace that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends it above all other Graces, from the beginning to the end of this Chapter, for he ſaith, though he had the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152622:11"/>Gift of Propheſie, and underſtood all Myſteries, and all Knowledge, and though he had all Faith, ſo that he could remove Mountains, and had not Charity, he was nothing. So that, my Beloved, though we have all theſe great Gifts and Graces, yet if we have not Charity, we are as if we had nothing; though we beſtow all our Goods to feed the Poor, though we give our Bodies to be burned, and have not Charity, it profiteth us nothing.</p>
            <p>You have heard out of this Scripture, that if you had all the Gifts and Graces the Scripture doth afford, yet if you have not Love, you have nothing. In the Firſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of St. <hi>John,</hi> Chap. 3. Ver. 7. it is ſaid, <hi>For this is the Meſſage ye have heard from the beginning, that we ſhould love one another.</hi> And again in the ſame Epiſtle, Chap. 2. Verſe 10. <hi>He that loveth his Brother abideth in the light, and there is no occaſion of ſtumbling in him.</hi> And again in the ſame Epiſtle, Chap. 3. Verſe 23. <hi>And this is his Commandment, that we ſhould believe on the Name of his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and love one another, as he gave us Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment.</hi> Again in the ſame Epiſtle, Chap. 4. Ver. 7, 8. <hi>Beloved, let us love one another, for love is of God, and every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God; he that loveth not, knoweth not God, for God is love.</hi> And in the ſame Chapter, Ver. 16. <hi>And we have known and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the love that God hath to us: God is love, and he that dwelleth in love dwelleth in God, and God in him: Herein is our love made perfect, that we may have boldneſs in the day of Judgment, becauſe as he is, ſo are we in this world.</hi> And Ver. 18. <hi>There is no fear in love, but perfect love caſteth out fear: becauſe fear hath torment: he that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is not made perfect in love:</hi> And ſo to the end of the Chapter, <hi>If any man ſay I love God, and hateth his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152622:11"/>he is a Lyar; for he that loveth not his Brother whom he both ſeen, how can be love God whom he hath not ſeen? And this Commandment have we from him, that he that loveth God, love his Brother alſo.</hi> In the ſecond Epiſtle, Verſe the 5th, <hi>Now I beſeech thee Lady, not as though I wrote a new Commandment unto thee, but that we had from the beginning, that we love one another; and this is love, that we walk after his Commandment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having ſpoken ſomething of Faith and Hope, we come now to Charity, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> commends above other Graces. Charity extends it ſelf into two Branches, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Love. 2. Good Works, which are the Fruits of Love. S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking in the commendation of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſaith, <hi>Though I have Faith ſo that I could remove Mountains, and have not Charity, it is but as ſounding Braſs, or a tinkling Cimbal.</hi> And a Father ſaith, <hi>Magna fructus Spiritus ſancto, Charity is the great Fruit of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Love is of ſo kind a Nature, that it envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, it is not ſelf-willed, nor eaſily provoked, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no evil, doth no evil; and is of ſo kind an affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that from it ſprings all other good Graces. This was the Advice of that good old Preacher Saint <hi>John</hi> the Divine, <hi>Little Children,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>love one another.</hi> It was the advice of our Saviour Chriſt to them that asked him the way to Heaven, or which was the Great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, ſaith he, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy mind, and with all thy ſtrength, and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf; on theſe two hang the Law and the Prophets:</hi> As much as to ſay, on theſe hang the great matters of our Salvation, the Law and the Goſpel. Love is of ſo peaceable a Nature, that it maketh our Enemies to be at peace with us. As for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152622:12"/>Example, when there was a Malefactor hired to kill his King, the King gave him ſuch loving words, and ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on him, that he could not execute his malicious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
            <p>You ſee then that Love is of ſo winning a temper, that it makes our Enemies to be at peace with us, that they cannot execute their malicious Deſigns. It is of ſuch a winning moderation, that many times it makes our Enemies to be our Friends; as ſaith a Father, <hi>Omnia vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit amor,</hi> Love overcomes all things. O my beloved Brethren, let us take care that a true and hearty love be in every one of us both towards God and towards our Neighbour, and then we may be ſure that the love of God dwelleth in us, and we in him; for God himſelf is love, and in him is no hatred. O my beloved Brethren, let us ſee that we eſteem and prize this great Grace of Love, as a great Jewel proceeding from the Holy Ghoſt. What a great benefit and joy is it to us and to our ſouls, to have the great God of Heaven and Earth to dwell in us and we in him! And having this Treaſure, we have all the Joys of Heaven and Earth.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now ſpeak ſomething by way of Reproof: Firſt, To the Common Enemy the Popiſh Faction. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, To the Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>And firſt to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who will have no Charity with us; but inſtead of Charity, they Plot miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief againſt us; they contrive to deſtroy our Bodies as well as our Souls. Although we are out of their Church, and they have nothing to do with us in their Church Diſcipline, yet they will uncharitably and maliciouſly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152622:12"/>Excommunicate us, both Gods Vicegerent the King, and all his Subjects, and put us into the ſtate of Damnation, as they think; though we know it worketh more for our good than for our hurt; ſo that they prove them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be no good Chriſtians, to be out of Charity with us who never meant any hurt.</p>
            <p>The next ſort that are to be reproved, are the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, from the Presbyterian to the Quakers, who break the Bands of love and Charity with us of the true Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopal Church of <hi>England:</hi> I wiſh their Repentance may be their Puniſhment. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the Acts of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, when he was brought before <hi>Ananias</hi> the High-Prieſt, when he commanded him to be ſmitten, <hi>Paul</hi> reviled him, and called him, <hi>Thou whited wall, &amp;c.</hi> thoſe that ſtood by told <hi>Paul, Doſt thou revile Gods High-Prieſt? Paul</hi> rebuked himſelf, and ſaid, <hi>I wiſt not that he was the High-Prieſt, it is written by</hi> Moſes, <hi>thou ſhalt not revile the Gods, nor ſpeak evil of the Ruler of my People.</hi> I fear, and 'tis much to be feared, that many of theſe Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have ſpoke evil, and reviled the King, and Gods Prieſts, and ſpoke evil of the Ruler of Gods People.</p>
            <p>Again, They break the bond of Love in going out from us, becauſe they were not of us: <hi>If they had been of us, they would have kept with us,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>John;</hi> They break the Bond of Charity which cauſe Diviſions as ſaith S. <hi>Paul, Mark them which cauſe Diviſions, and avoid them, contrary to the Doctrine which we have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for they ſerve not the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:152622:13"/>
            <p>A third ſort of men to be reproved, are thoſe which neither love God, nor their Neighbour, nor themſelves, but covetouſly and miſerably pinch both back and belly, to heap up Riches, and they know not who ſhall inherit them; and ſet their hearts upon their Money-bags, and as it were make them their Gods. <hi>The love of Money is the root of all Evil,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>and hath cauſed men to run into divers Errours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Lord grant that all thoſe that have broken the Bonds of Love and Charity with us, may ſee their Errours and repent; the Lord give them Grace, that they may with true love and charity come in to us again, they they with us, and we with them, may ſerve the Lord in true love and ſincerity, to the Glory of God, and the benefit of our Souls at the laſt day, that we may be received into thoſe everlaſting Manſions where there ſhall be no Diviſion, but Peace, Unity, and Love.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells us that Charity ſhall cover a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Sins: O my Beloved, let us therefore embrace Charity, for it will cover a multitude of our ſins. How ought we therefore to prize this great Grace of Love, which is Charity, and walk therein, for it proceedeth from the Spirit of God, and is one of the great Fruits of the Holy Ghoſt, and to make ſuch uſe of it in our Lives and Converſations as becometh good Chriſtians; that our Love may be to God and to our Neighbour in deed and in truth; that God may dwell in us, and we in him; and if we do theſe things we ſhall never fall. If you would fulfill the Royal Law according to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>You muſt love your Neighbour as your ſelf,</hi> Jam. 2.8.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:152622:13"/>
            <p>We come now to the next Branch of Charity, which is Good Works: In this Epiſtle of St. <hi>James, Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 14. and ſo to the end of the Chapter, it is ſaid, <hi>what doth it profit, my Brethren, though a man have faith, and have not Works, can faith ſave him? If a Brother or Siſter be naked and deſtitute of daily food, and one of you ſay unto him depart in peace, be you warmed, and be you filled, notwithſtanding ye give them not thoſe things which are needful to the body, what doth it profit?</hi> Even ſo Faith, if it have not works is dead, it being alone: Yea a man may ſay thou haſt Faith, and I have Works; ſhew me thy Faith without thy works, and I will ſhew thee my Faith by my Works. Thou believeſt there is one God, thou doſt well; the Devils alſo believe and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: But wilt thou know, O vain man! that Faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Works is dead. Was not <hi>Abraham</hi> our Father ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by Works, when he Offered up his Son <hi>Iſaac</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Altar? Seeſt thou how Faith wrought with his Works, and by Works was Faith made perfect. You ſee then that by Works a man is juſtified, and not by Faith only: As the Body without the Spirit is dead, ſo Faith without works is dead alſo.</p>
            <p>You ſee, my beloved, that 'tis the benefit of Good Works which makes our Faith perfect; it brings us much into the favour of God. He that gives to the poor, lends to the Lord, and doubtleſs he will pay us again with bleſſings Temporal and Spiritual: If we lend him our Earthly Treaſure, he will pay us again with Heavenly Treaſure, which is far better. God loveth us if we give chearfully, for God loveth a chearful giver. <hi>To do good, and to communicate to the poor forget not, for with ſuch Sacrifices God is well pleaſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:152622:14"/>
            <p>Love and Good Works make our Faith to ſhine in its luſtre, like precious Jewels in a Kings Crown: Faith, Hope, and Charity may be compared to the Tree of Life in the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> whereof Faith is the Stock, Hope is the Branches, and Charity, which is Love and Good Works, is the Fruit which hangs on the Tree of Life, and they that eat of that Fruit, ſhall live for ever in the Kingdom of Heaven. Again, Good Works which proceed from love will go with us to the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and plead for us; for Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaith in the <hi>Revelations, Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, even ſo ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and their works follow them.</hi> You ſee here, my beloved, that the benefit of our Charity will follow us after death, and will not leave us till we come to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. It is to be feared, the want of Good Works was the Cauſe why Chriſt pronounced that Sentence againſt thoſe that fawned on him, as it is ſaid in S. <hi>Matthews</hi> Goſpel, the ſeventh Chapter, the two and twentieth and three and twentieth Verſes, where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Many will ſay unto me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not propheſied in thy Name, and in thy Name have caſt out Devils, and in thy Name done many wondrous works? I ſhall profeſs to them, I never knew them, depart from me ye workers of Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You would think thoſe Miniſters to be Saints, who have propheſied in Gods Name, and in his Name have caſt out Devils, and in his Name done many wondrous works. If thoſe that in Chriſt's Name work Miracles, and in his Name do many wondrous works, be called by Chriſt, Workers of Iniquity, and bid depart from him, he never knew them; what will become of ſuch, in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152622:14"/>the end of the World, who do no Good Works?</p>
            <p>O all you that are called of God to be Miniſters of his Goſpel, and are of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> the Lord grant you may be found in all Good Works, that while you preach to others, your ſelves may not be counted Caſtaways, nor found amongſt thoſe whom Chriſt calls Workers of Iniquity. Now the Lord grant every one of us, from the King to the Miniſters of Gods Word, and to all the reſt of the People, that all of us may be found in Love and Charity, and in doing of Good Works, that we may be placed amongſt that little Flock which ſtandeth at Chriſts right hand at the laſt day, and hear that bleſſed Sentence, which is ſpoken in the Goſpel of S. <hi>Matthew,</hi> Chap. 25. Verſes 32, 33, 34. and ſo on, <hi>Before him ſhall be gathered all Nations, and he ſhall ſeparate them one from another, as a Shepherd ſeparateth his Sheep from the Goats, and he ſhall ſet the Sheep on his right hand, and the Goats on his left; Then ſhall the King ſay to them on his right hand, Come ye bleſſed of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inherit ye the Kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the World; for I was hungry and you gave me meat, thirſty and you gave me drink; I was a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ye took me in, naked and ye clothed me, ſick and ye viſited me, in priſon and ye came unto me. Then ſhall the righteous anſwer him, ſaying, when ſaw we thee hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and fed thee; naked, and clothed thee; thirſty, and gave thee drink; when ſaw we thee a Stranger, and took thee in; or when ſaw we thee ſick and in Priſon, and came unto thee? And the King ſhall anſwer them, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as ye have done it to one of the leaſt of theſe my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ye have done it unto me.</hi> You hear, my Beloved Brethren, from our Saviour Jeſus Chriſts own words,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152622:15"/>that Charity which is the cauſe of Good Works is the chief cauſe why our Saviour pronounceth us bleſſed, and of our inheriting of the Kingdom of Heaven; Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is the cauſe of bleſſings in this World, and of our happineſs in the world to come.</p>
            <p>Then ſhall he ſay alſo to them on his left hand, <hi>Depart ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels; for I was hungry and ye gave me no meat, thirſty and ye gave me no drink; I was a Stranger and ye took me not in, naked and ye clothed me not, ſick and in Priſon and ye viſited me not: Then ſhall they anſwer him, ſaying, Lord, when ſaw we thee an hungred, and thirſty, or naked, or ſick, or in priſon, and did not miniſter unto thee? Then ſhall he anſwer them, ſaying, Verily, verily, I ſay unto you, in as much as ye did it not unto one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me: And theſe ſhall go into everlaſting puniſhment; but the righteous into life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O my beloved, you may ſee that the want of Good Works is the cauſe of that ſad Sentence pronounced againſt the wicked; if they had done Good Works they might have obtained the Joys of Heaven, and there to have lived with the Saints and Angels for evermore; and for want of Good Works they are ſentenced into Hell, there to remain in torments for evermore, world without end.</p>
            <p>O my beloved Brethren, ſeeing that Faith, Hope, and Charity are all linked together, and that Love and Charity are the perfection of our Faith, without which Faith is dead, the Lord grant that every one of us may unite together in love, as well Diſſenters as others, who went out from us; the Lord grant they may come in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152622:15"/>to us again, and that we may unite together in love, and ſerve God together in love, without which we ſhall never come into the Kingdom of Heaven; that the Lord may ſend his bleſſings amongſt us, and delight to do us good, that our light may ſhine like Stars in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for this Church Militant is to fit us for the Church Triumphant, where there is no diviſion nor diſſention, but all are of one heart and of one mind. The Lord grant that every one of us be found in Love and Good Works, that we may all meet in the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> together, there with the Angels and Arch-Angels, and all the Heavenly Hoſt, to ſing <hi>Hallelujahs</hi> and <hi>Gloria Pater,</hi> to God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, who hath made us, redeemed us, ſanctified us, and juſtified us; to whom be attributed all Might, Majeſty, and Dominion, both now and evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A word of Uſe and Application to our ſelves, and of the Benefits we ſhall receive by this great Grace of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>And firſt, It will cover a multitude of ſins, as ſaith S. <hi>James,</hi> Chap. 2. Ver. 17.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It makes our Faith perfect, without which it is dead. The Lord grant that every one of us may underſtand his Faith ſo well, that he may not deceive himſelf, for without Good Works Faith is dead. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is the Band that ties all our Graces together, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which they are all as nothing.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Charity makes God to dwell in us, and we in him; it makes us to be at peace with all men, it overcomes the malice of wicked men, and makes them to be our Friends. Charity with the Good Works which ſpring from it, is the cauſe why Chriſt calls us, Bleſſed of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152622:16"/>his Father, in that glorious Sentence at the laſt day: It is one of the chief cauſes that we inherit the Kingdom of Heaven, which was prepared for us from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the World. Chriſt tells us, that he was hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and we fed him, thirſty and we gave him Drink, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and we clothed him; and ſo on: as you may read in the 25th <hi>Chapter</hi> of S. <hi>Matthews</hi> Goſpel, from the 34th Verſe to the end of the Chapter.</p>
            <p>Again, the want of Charity and Good Works was the cauſe why Chriſt pronounced that curſed Sentence to thoſe wicked men on his left hand; <hi>Go ye curſed into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels; for I was hungry and ye fed me not, thirſty and ye gave me no drink, naked and ye clothed me not, ſick and priſon and ye viſited me not: And they ſhall ask him, when ſaw we thee in this condition? And he ſhall anſwer them, In as much as ye have not done it to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye have not done it unto me:</hi> And theſe ſhall go into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting puniſhment, but the righteous into life eternal. Now I beſeech you, Brethren, to take good notice, and to lay it to heart, that the want of Good Works was the chief cauſe that the Wicked went into everlaſting Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. And I beſeech you, Brethren, in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that every one of us, both Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and People, ſtrive to be found in ſuch a meaſure of Good Works, as that we may be accepted of by Chriſt, that ſo we may obtain life eternal. The Lord grant that every one of us may follow Charity in all our lives and Converſations, it being the whole perfection of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, without which we ſhall never go to Heaven, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we have heard a thouſand Sermons, and practiſed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152622:16"/>the Doctrines of them all, yet if this Doctrine of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity be wanting, all profiteth nothing.</p>
            <p>Now all good Chriſtian People, I beſeech you in the Lord, as well Diſſenters as others, to come in to the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Epiſcopal Church of <hi>England,</hi> from which you went out, and there to ſerve God in Unity, Love, and Charity; for this Church Militant is to fit us for the Church Triumphant, where there is no diviſion nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention, and there to ſing <hi>Hallelujah</hi> with the Heavenly Hoſt for evermore. Which the Lord of his Mercy grant, for Jeſus Chriſts ſake, our bleſſed Redeemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152622:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152622:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
